<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM "jersey.ent" >
%ents;
]>

<chapter>
  <title>Building and testing Jersey</title>

<section>
<title>Checking out the source</title>
<para>
The Jersey source code is available from the Subversion repository located at
<ulink url="https://jersey.dev.java.net/svn/jersey">https://jersey.dev.java.net/svn/jersey</ulink>.
</para>
<para>
To check out the trunk where active development on the next release occurs use
the following command:
<programlisting>
svn checkout https://jersey.dev.java.net/svn/jersey/trunk/jersey jersey -username &lt;username&gt;
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
Stable releases of Jersey are tagged in the location
<ulink url="https://jersey.dev.java.net/svn/jersey/tags">https://jersey.dev.java.net/svn/jersey/tags</ulink>.
</para>
<para>
The source code may be browsed using
<ulink url="http://fisheye4.atlassian.com/browse/jersey">FishEye</ulink>.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Building using Maven</title>
<para>
Java SE 6 or greater is required. Maven 2.2.1 or greater is recommended.
</para>
<para>
It is recommended to build the whole of Jersey after you have initially checked
out the source code.
To build all of Jersey use the following command from the checked out
<literal>jersey</literal> directory:
<programlisting>
mvn clean install
</programlisting>
To skip all the tests do:
<programlisting>
mvn -Dmaven.test.skip=true clean install
</programlisting>
The following maven options are recommended:
<programlisting>
-Xmx1048m -XX:PermSize=64M -XX:MaxPermSize=128M
</programlisting>
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Testing</title>
<para>
Jersey contains many unit tests. Most of these are not really unit tests per-say
and are functional tests using the JUnit test framework because it is very
convientient for execution and reporting.
</para>
<para>
Some modules have specific tests but most tests associated with testing the
jersey-core, jersey-client and jersey-server modules are located in the
jersey-test module. This module can take some time to execute all the tests so
it is recommended that you pick the appropriate tests to run related to the
particular area that is being investigated. For example,
using:
<programlisting>
mvn -Dtest=&lt;pattern&gt; test
</programlisting>
where <literal>pattern</literal> may be a comma separated set of names matching
tests.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Continuous building and testing with Hudson</title>
<para>
Jersey is built, tested and deployed on Solaris, Windows and Linux using an
interal Hudson server. The Jersey Hudson jobs are available publically
at <ulink url="http://hudson.glassfish.org/job/Jersey-trunk-multiplatform/">
    http://hudson.glassfish.org/job/Jersey-trunk-multiplatform/</ulink>.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Using NetBeans</title>
<para>
NetBeans 6.8 or greater has excellent maven support. The Jersey maven
modules can be loaded, built and tested in NetBeans without any additional
project-specific requirements.
</para>
</section>

</chapter>
