<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM "jersey.ent" >
%ents;
]>
<section>
    <title>Hypermedia Actions</title>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>It is generally understood that, in order to follow the REST style, URIs should be
            assigned to anything of interest (resources) and a few, well-defined operations should
            be used to interact with these resources. For example, the state of a purchase order
            resource can be updated by POSTing or PATCHing a new value for the its state field.
            However, there are actions that cannot be easily mapped to read or write operations on
            resources. These operations are inherently more complex and their details are rarely of
            interest to clients. For example, given a purchase order resource, the operation of
            setting its state to <literal>REVIEWED</literal> may involve a number of different steps
            such as: <orderedlist>
                <listitem>checking the customer's credit status</listitem>
                <listitem>reserving product inventory</listitem>
                <listitem>verifying per-customer quantity limits.</listitem>
            </orderedlist> Clearly, this <emphasis>workflow</emphasis> cannot be equated to simply
            updating a field on a resource. Moreover, clients are generally uninterested in the
            details behind these type of workflows, and in some cases computing the final state of a
            resource on the client side, as required for a PUT operation, is impractical or
            impossible.</para>
        <para>We call these operations <emphasis>actions</emphasis> and, because they are of
            interest to us, we turn them into <emphasis>action resources</emphasis>. An action
            resource is a sub-resource defined for the purpose of exposing workflow-related
            operations on parent resources. As sub-resources, action resources are identified by
            URIs that are relative to their parent. For instance, the following are examples of
            action resources:
            <programlisting>    http://.../orders/1/review
    http://.../orders/1/pay
    http://.../orders/1/ship</programlisting>
            for purchase order "1" identified by <literal>http://.../orders/1</literal>.</para>
        <para>Action resources as first-class citizens provide the necessary tools for developers to
            implement HATEOAS. A set of action resources defines --via their link relationships-- a
                <emphasis>contract</emphasis> with clients that has the potential to evolve over
            time depending on the application's state. For instance, assuming purchase orders are
            only reviewed once, the <literal>review</literal> action will become unavailable and the
                <literal>pay</literal> action will become available after an order is
        reviewed.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Hypermedia by Example</title>
        <para>The notion of action resources naturally leads to discussions about improved client
            APIs to support them. Given that action resources are identified by URIs, no additional
            API is really necessary, but the use of client-side proxies and method invocations to
            trigger these actions seems quite natural. Additionally, the use of client proxies
            introduces a level of indirection that enables better support for <emphasis>server
                evolution</emphasis>, i.e. the ability of a server's contract to support certain
            changes without breaking existing clients. Finally, it has been argued that using client
            proxies is simply more natural for developers and less error prone as fewer URIs need to
            be constructed.</para>
        <para>Rather than presenting all these extensions abstractly, we shall illustrate their use
            via an example. The complete example can found in <ulink
                url="http://download.java.net/maven/2/com/sun/jersey/experimental/hypermedia-action/hypermedia-action-sample/"
                >hypermedia-action-sample</ulink>. The <emphasis>Purchase Ordering System</emphasis>
            exemplifies a system in which customers can submit orders and where orders are guided by
            a workflow that includes states like <literal>REVIEWED</literal>,
            <literal>PAYED</literal> and <literal>SHIPPED</literal>. The system's model is comprised
            of 4 entities: <literal>Order</literal>, <literal>Product</literal>,
            <literal>Customer</literal> and <literal>Address</literal>. These model entities are
            controlled by 3 resource classes: <literal>OrderResource</literal>,
                <literal>CustomerResource</literal> and <literal>ProductResource</literal>.
            Addresses are sub-resources that are also controlled by
            <literal>CustomerResource</literal>. An order instance refers to a single customer, a
            single address (of that customer) and one or more products. The XML representation (or
            view) of a sample order is shown below. <programlisting><![CDATA[    <order>
        <id>1</id>
        <customer>http://.../customers/21</customer>
        <shippingAddress>http://.../customers/21/address/1</shippingAddress>
        <orderItems>
            <product>http://.../products/3345</product>
            <quantity>1</quantity>
        </orderItems>
        <status>RECEIVED</status>
    </order>]]></programlisting> Note the use of URIs to refer to each component of an order. This
            form of <emphasis>serialization by reference</emphasis> is supported in Jersey using
            JAXB beans and the <literal>@XmlJavaTypeAdapter</literal> annotation. An
                <literal>XmlAdapter</literal> is capable of mapping an object reference in the model
            to a URI. Refer to <ulink
                url="http://download.java.net/maven/2/com/sun/jersey/experimental/hypermedia-action/hypermedia-action-sample/"
                >hypermedia-action-sample</ulink> for more information on how this mapping is
        implemented.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Server API</title>
        <para>The server API introduces 3 new annotation types: <literal>@Action</literal>,
                <literal>@ContextualActionSet</literal> and
            <literal>@HypermediaController</literal>. The <literal>@Action</literal> annotation
            identifies a sub-resource as a <emphasis>named action</emphasis>. The
                <literal>@ContextualActionSet</literal> is used to support contextual contracts and
            must annotate a method that returns a set of action names. Finally,
                <literal>@HypermediaController</literal> marks a resource class as a
                <emphasis>hypermedia controller class</emphasis>: a class with one more methods
            annotated with <literal>@Action</literal> and at most one method annotated with
                <literal>@ContextualActionSet</literal>.</para>
        <para>The following example illustrates the use of all these annotation types to define the
                <literal>OrderResource</literal> controller.<footnote>
                <para>Several details about this class are omitted for clarity. The reader is
                    referred to the hypermedia sample for more details.</para>
            </footnote>
            <programlisting linenumbering="numbered"
            >    @Path("/orders/{id}")
    @HypermediaController(
        model=Order.class,
        linkType=LinkType.LINK_HEADERS)
    public class OrderResource {
        
        private Order order;
    
        ...
        
        @GET @Produces("application/xml")
        public Order getOrder(@PathParam("id") String id) {      
            return order;
        }
        
        @POST @Action("review") @Path("review")
        public void review(@HeaderParam("notes") String notes) {
            ...
            order.setStatus(REVIEWED);
        }
        
        @POST @Action("pay") @Path("pay")
        public void pay(@QueryParam("newCardNumber") String newCardNumber) {
            ...
            order.setStatus(PAYED);
        }
        
        @PUT @Action("ship") @Path("ship")
        @Produces("application/xml")
        @Consumes("application/xml")
        public Order ship(Address newShippingAddress) {
            ...
            order.setStatus(SHIPPED);
            return order;
        }
        
        @POST @Action("cancel") @Path("cancel")
        public void cancel(@QueryParam("notes") String notes) {
            ...
            order.setStatus(CANCELED);
        }
    }</programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>The <literal>@HypermediaController</literal> annotation above indicates that this
            resource class is a hypermedia controller for the <literal>Order</literal> class. Each
            method annotated with <literal>@Action</literal> defines a link relationship and
            associated action resource. These methods are also annotated with
            <literal>@Path</literal> to make a sub-resource. There does not appear to be a need to
            use <literal>@Action</literal> and <literal>@Path</literal> simultaneously, but without
            the latter some resource methods may become ambiguous. In the future, we hope to
            eliminate the use of <literal>@Path</literal> when <literal>@Action</literal> is
            present. The element <literal>linkType</literal> selects the way in which URIs
            corresponding to action resources are serialized: in this case, using link headers.
            These link headers become part of the an order's representation. For instance, an order
            in the <literal>RECEIVED</literal> state, i.e. an order that can only be reviewed or
            canceled, will be represented as follows. <programlisting>    <![CDATA[Link: <http://.../orders/1/review>;rel=review;op=POST
    Link: <http://.../orders/1/cancel>;rel=cancel;op=POST
    <order>
        <id>1</id>
        <customer>http://.../customers/21</customer>
        <shippingAddress>http://.../customers/21/address/1</shippingAddress>
        <orderItems>
            <product>http://.../products/3345</product>
            <quantity>1</quantity>
        </orderItems>
        <status>RECEIVED</status>
    </order>]]></programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>Without a method annotated with <literal>@ContextualActionSet</literal>, all actions
            are available at all times regardless of the state of an order. The following method can
            be provided to define a contextual contract for this resource. <programlisting
                linenumbering="numbered"><![CDATA[    @ContextualActionSet
    public Set<String> getContextualActionSet() {
        Set<String> result = new HashSet<String>();
        switch (order.getStatus()) {
            case RECEIVED:
                result.add("review");
                result.add("cancel");
                break;
            case REVIEWED:
                result.add("pay");
                result.add("cancel");
                break;
            case PAYED:
                result.add("ship");
                break;
            case CANCELED:
            case SHIPPED:
                break;
        }
        return result;
    }]]></programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>This method returns a set of action names based on the order's internal state; the
            values returned in this set correspond to the <literal>@Action</literal> annotations in
            the controller. For example, this contextual contract prevents shipping an order that
            has not been payed by only including the <literal>ship</literal> action in the
                <literal>PAYED</literal> state.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Client API</title>
        <para>Although action resources can be accessed using traditional APIs for REST, including
            Jersey's client API, the use of client-side proxies and method invocations to trigger
            these actions seems quite natural. As we shall see, the use of client proxies also
            introduces a level of indirection that enables better support for server evolution,
            permitting the definition of contracts with various degrees of coupling.</para>
        <para>Client proxies are created based on <emphasis>hypermedia controller
            interfaces</emphasis>. Hypermedia controller interfaces are Java interfaces annotated by
                <literal>@HypermediaController</literal> that, akin to the server side API, specify
            the name of a model class and the type of serialization to use for action resource URIs.
            The client-side model class should be based on the representation returned by the
            server; in particular, in our example the client-side model for an
            <literal>Order</literal> uses instances of <literal>URI</literal> to link an order to a
            customer, an address and a list of products. <programlisting linenumbering="numbered"
            >    @HypermediaController(
        model=Order.class,
        linkType=LinkType.LINK_HEADERS)
    public interface OrderController {
        
        public Order getModel();
        
        @Action("review")
        public void review(@Name("notes") String notes);
        
        @POST @Action("pay")
        public void pay(@QueryParam("newCardNumber") String newCardNumber);
        
        @Action("ship")
        public Order ship(Address newShippingAddress);
        
        @Action("cancel")
        public void cancel(@Name("notes") String notes);
    }</programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>The <literal>@Action</literal> annotation associates an interface method with a link
            relation and hence an action resource on the server. Thus, invoking a method on the
            generated proxy results in an interaction with the corresponding action resource. The
            way in which the method invocation is mapped to an HTTP request depends on the
            additional annotations specified in the interface. For instance, the
            <literal>pay</literal> action in the example above indicates that it must use a
                <literal>POST</literal> and that the <literal>String</literal> parameter
                <literal>newCardNumber</literal> must be passed as a query parameter. This is an
            example of a <emphasis>static</emphasis> contract in which the client has built-in
            knowledge of the way in which an action is defined by the server.</para>
        <para>In contrast, the <literal>review</literal> action only provides a name for its
            parameter using the <literal>@Name</literal> annotation. This is an example of a
                <emphasis>dynamic</emphasis> contract in which the client is only coupled to the
                <literal>review</literal> link relation and the knowledge that this relation
            requires <literal>notes</literal> to be supplied. The exact interaction with the
                <literal>review</literal> action must therefore be discovered dynamically and the
                <literal>notes</literal> parameter mapped accordingly. The Jersey client runtime
            uses WADL fragments that describe action resources to map these method calls into HTTP
            requests.</para>
        <para>The following sample shows how to use <literal>OrderController</literal> to generate a
            proxy to review, pay and ship an order. For the sake of the example, we assume the
            customer that submitted the order has been suspended and needs to be activated before
            the order is reviewed. For that purpose, the client code retrieves the customer URI from
            the order's model and obtains an instance of <literal>CustomerController</literal>.<footnote>
                <para>
                    <literal>CustomerController</literal> is a hypermedia controller interface akin
                    to <literal>OrderController</literal> which is omitted since it does not
                    highlight any additional feature.</para>
            </footnote>
            <programlisting linenumbering="numbered"
            >    // Instantiate Jersey's Client class
    Client client = new Client();
        
    // Create proxy for order and retrieve model
    OrderController orderCtrl = client.view(
        "http://.../orders/1", OrderController.class);
        
    // Create proxy for customer in order 1
    CustomerController customerCtrl = client.view(
        orderCtrl.getModel().getCustomer(),
        CustomerController.class);
        
    // Activate customer in order 1 
    customerCtrl.activate();
        
    // Review and pay order 
    orderCtrl.review("approve");
    orderCtrl.pay("123456789");
        
    // Ship order 
    Address newAddress = getNewAddress();
    orderCtrl.ship(newAddress);</programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>The client runtime will automatically update the action set throughout a conversation:
            for example, even though the <literal>review</literal> action does not produce a result,
            the HTTP response to that action still includes a list of link headers defining the
            contextual action set, which in this case will consist of the <literal>pay</literal> and
                <literal>cancel</literal> actions but not the <literal>ship</literal> action. An 
            attempt to interact with any action not in the contextual action set will result in
            a client-side exception if using proxies (as shown above), or a server-side exception 
            if using some other API.</para>
        <para>The following annotations are allowed in hypermedia controller interfaces:
                <literal>@Name</literal>, <literal>@Consumes</literal>,
            <literal>@Produces</literal>, <literal>@CookieParam</literal>,
            <literal>@FormParam</literal>, <literal>@HeaderParam</literal>,
            <literal>@QueryParam</literal>, as well as any HTTP method annotation like
                <literal>@POST</literal>, <literal>@PUT</literal>, etc. All other annotations not
            listed here are unsupported at this time (of note, <literal>@MatrixParam</literal> is
            not supported). The <literal>@Name</literal> annotation used in Jersey is defined in
                <literal>com.sun.jersey.core.hypermedia</literal>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Server Evolution</title>
        <para>In the last section, we have seen how the use of client proxies based on
                <emphasis>partially</emphasis> annotated interfaces facilitates server evolution. An
            interface method annotated with <literal>@Action</literal> and <literal>@Name</literal>
            represents a <emphasis>loosely-coupled</emphasis> contract with a server. Changes to
            action resource URIs, HTTP methods and parameter types on the server will not require a
            client re-spin. Naturally, as in all client-server architectures, it is always possible
            to break backward compatibility, but the ability to support more dynamic contracts
            --usually at the cost of additional processing time-- is still an area of investigation.</para>
        <para> We see this form of hypermedia support in Jersey as a small step in this direction,
            showing the potential of using dynamic meta-data for the definition of these type of
            contracts. The use of dynamic meta-data requires the server to return WADL fragments
            when using <literal>OPTIONS</literal> on an action resource URI. When dynamic meta-data
            is not available (for example if using an older version of Jersey on the server) client
            interfaces should be fully annotated and a <emphasis>tighly-coupled</emphasis> contract
            should be used instead.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Configuring Hypermedia in Jersey</title>
        <para>There are a few configuration options in  <ulink
            url="http://download.java.net/maven/2/com/sun/jersey/experimental/hypermedia-action/hypermedia-action-sample/"
            >hypermedia-action-sample</ulink> that are worth highlighting. First, a
            special filter factory <literal>HypermediaFilterFactory</literal> must
            be enabled. This can be done programmatically by adding
            <programlisting>com.sun.jersey.server.hypermedia.filter.HypermediaFilterFactory</programlisting> to the list defined by
            <programlisting>com.sun.jersey.spi.container.ResourceFilters</programlisting> or
            declaratively in the application's <literal>web.xml</literal> file. Refer to the Java class
            <literal>com.sun.jersey.samples.hypermedia.Main</literal> in the hypermedia sample for an example of how
            to do this using Grizzly (which can be executed with <literal>mvn install exec:java</literal>). Second, hypermedia applications must included the
            following Maven runtime dependencies:
            <programlisting><![CDATA[
        <dependency>
            <groupId>com.sun.jersey.experimental.hypermedia-action</groupId>
            <artifactId>hypermedia-action-server</artifactId>
            <version>${jersey-version}</version>
        </dependency>
        <dependency>
            <groupId>com.sun.jersey.experimental.hypermedia-action</groupId>
            <artifactId>hypermedia-action-client</artifactId>
            <version>${jersey-version}</version>
        </dependency>]]></programlisting></para>
        <para>
            Last, even though the annotation <literal>@HypermediaController</literal> has
            a <literal>linkType</literal> element, only the <literal>LinkType.LINK_HEADERS</literal>
            option is currently supported and must be used by both clients and servers.
        </para>
    </section>
</section>
